[SPEAKER_00]: So, it seems very rare that people pick up the practice and take it all the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm wondering whether it takes a certain type of character to practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it doesn't take like, I don't know, one of the sixteen personality traits or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Character doesn't mean like, yeah, the random personality habits that you have built up over your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you need to have to practice dhamma, well, the Buddha mentioned it, like, multiple times.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the most important ones would be somebody who
[SPEAKER_01]: ...sees themselves or is like actively looks for their shortcomings, rather than tries to cover them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or looks for their... what they... or not necessarily shortcomings, but like things that they can still improve over the things that, you know, they feel confident about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's that sutta where the Buddha says, thinking that you understand what you don't understand, being that kind of conceited attitude that like you can't accept that your worldview needs to change, that your values need to change,
[SPEAKER_01]: That the values you currently have are the ones, are the reason why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That whole willingness to accept that,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, practice it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just one time I accept it and then, you know, I just live the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, actually, you're gonna have to actively evolve.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, absence of complacency, basically, is the number one character trait that you need to have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-contentment with wholesome or good... things that you think are good.
[SPEAKER_01]: You look... you see the glass half empty rather than half full, as the saying goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the other one would be, well, bravery, like, you know, recognizing... because when you don't have courage, when you don't have bravery, you will either
[SPEAKER_01]: Not practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give up the practice, because it's too hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you would try to mold the practice into what you want it to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, so that you don't have to face the things that actually are involved in the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's the second one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like recognizing, being able to see that something is very difficult, and still not feel daunted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still realize and not lose perspective that it factually has to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, how even in worldly terms, some people, you know, there may be some thing that has to be fixed, let's say a construction project or something, and it's like pretty bad if you don't fix it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for them, the discomfort of recognizing that this has to be done is so big,
[SPEAKER_01]: That they actually don't do it, rather than, you know, prioritizing the the perception of harm of what's going to happen, because that's an absence of that, you could say, courage.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that it's not a blind, like, you you you you're chasing after difficulty as a kind of... to get a kick out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the things that are factually difficult already,
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the same time need to be done, you're not afraid of holding those two ideas together.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... but it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, someone tries to imagine, then, what someone who is courageous is like.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might imagine someone who is already full of courage, and even though something seems impossible, they're not fazed or daunted by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, it must be easy for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, that doesn't come from... Like, if it's easy for them,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not because of a random fate thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because, let's say, if you don't have it, you have been actively cultivating habits in the opposite direction, that you can equally... you have to undo by, for example, it's all a matter of, like, when those situations come up, difficult situations, you have the chance to think about why it still has to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have a chance of reflecting on
[SPEAKER_01]: All the bad things that are going to happen if you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you choose not to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's more comfortable to just not do it and not accept that it should be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if at least you are able to maintain the clarity that it should be done, and you don't try to obscure that in order to not feel guilty, then you are like... you've at least walked through the door, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you will have the ability to, at some point, start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the opposite option, where you don't accept that it has to be done, then, even if you don't feel guilty, even if you feel completely at peace, that entire peace is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's the peace of delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's actually more important to be
[SPEAKER_01]: Aware of how things actually are, like the danger of sickness, aging, death, the peril that you are subjected to by not freeing yourself from craving because of all these calamities that are going to come to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more accurate to be aware of that and to make that recollection a part of your life than it is to be quote-unquote peaceful by not thinking about those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that peace will only increase
[SPEAKER_01]: The pain, and the surprise, and the the burden that will come to you, whenever things get ruined, which will happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a piece that's basically like... it's like taking a loan, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in the moment you feel... be feeling better, but what's waiting for you at the end of that is much worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like... you could say that's a character trait, like that somebody prefers to... like non-procrastination, for example, like somebody prefers to fix things when they're actually important, not like you're trying to find random work to do, but like if something is actually important, you tend to not rest until you've done it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems that these are qualities of really putting how you feel second.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not really part of the picture, in terms of your assessment of what you want to do, what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a character trait in itself, like being able to recognize that... keep perspective of, I need to do this independently of how I feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually something that declines with time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in the average person, you can see that it pretty much goes in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more people proliferate their senses and their mundane delights, the more difficult it is for them to do things when they're painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything needs to be kind of covered up in some immediate benefit in order to be doable.